מזל טוב. Mazel tov. Today's דף daf is קיג. kuf yud gimmel.
113. We start from the משנה. mishnah. We're still dealing with the
issue of knots
and let's take a look at the next משנה. mishnah. We had
discussed questions about knots that are forbidden, which are either completely permanent
knots or, according to the רמב״ם, Rambam, a combination of קשר אומן
kesher uman professional knot and permanent, but maybe not permanent forever like
רש״י Rashi would have it. Those that are permitted, that don't have
either of those qualities, are very temporary or are not professional and
so on, and those that are somewhat in the middle that are
rabbinically forbidden. Now let's look at this next משנה. mishnah. קושרים דלי
בפסקיא. koshin dli bipaskia.
You can tie a דלי, dli, a bucket, with a פסקיא, paskia,
a belt. So you have your bucket attached to the well, you
don't want it to fall down the well, so you tie it
to some outer structure of the well. But rather than using the
regular rope, you use a belt. So that's okay because who's going
to leave- you're not going to leave your belt there. You're obviously
going to undo it. So that's
important though because the nature of the
knot presumably is not saying something about the nature and the qualities
of the knot. Normally, obviously, a bucket would be tied to stay
on for a long period of time and presumably it would be
a strong knot. But since because contextually and from your subjective perspective,
you're only going to make it very temporary, that is enough to
make it permissible. אבל לא בחבל, aval lo b'chevel, but not with
a חבל, chevel, a rope, for obvious reasons that it's going to
be rabbinically, maybe even biblically forbidden depending on how permanent or professional
the knot will be. רבי יהודה מתיר. Rebbe Yehuda matir. Rebbe Yehuda
says no, you can even use a rope, which is surprising. וכללו
אמר רבי יהודה. ve-klalo amar Rebbe Yehuda. Now Rebbe Yehuda said a
general principle. כל קשר שאינו של קיימא אין חייבין עליו. kol kesher
she'eino shel kayama ein chayavin alav. Anything that's not permanent, you're not
חייב. chayav. So תוספות Tosafot says, what does that have to do
with the line he said before? First of all, we already said
if it's not permanent, you're not חייב. chayav. And second of all,
he's telling you that
you're allowed לכתחילה l'chatchila to tie it to a bucket. So that's
not just a question of not being חייב. chayav. So תוספות Tosafot
says, yeah, maybe it's really not going at all on the last
line we just said. It's going back on clarifying the very first
משנה mishnah that we talked about about the knots that you're חייב
chayav on and this is really a separate point of רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda not connected to the previous point. Okay. Let's look at
the גמרא. Gemara. חבל דמאי. chevel d'mai. What type of a rope
does רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda allow you to tie your bucket to
the well to? אילימא חבל דעלמא, i-lima chevel d'alma, a regular rope?
So רבי יהודה מתיר? Rebbe Yehuda matir? Rebbe Yehuda would allow it?
קשר של קיימא הוא. kesher shel kayama hu. It's a permanent knot.
And again, it's at least rabbinic if not biblical depending on the
degree of permanence or whether it's professional, so how could he allow
such a thing? And obviously if it's a rope you're going to
leave it there. אלא חבל דגרדי. ela chevel d'garde.
It's a rope used by weavers. So it looks pretty similar or
who knows, maybe an identical but certainly pretty similar to a normal
rope. But given the specific context that it's a weaver's rope, it's
something, I don't know the exact thing, whether it was a rope
that they wore around their body as a symbol of their profession
or whether it was a rope that they used somehow in some
type of professional capacity, but it certainly is not just a normal
rope. They're not going to leave it there. Come מוצאי שבת, motzaei
Shabbat, right? Now it's שבת, Shabbat, we need to draw water from
the well. Who's got a rope? So the weaver takes the sash
off of his garment or the rope, not the rope, the rope
off of his that he has available to him. But that doesn't
mean that there's no question that he's not going to leave it
there. But it looks pretty similar to a normal rope and that's
the debate. So let's take a look. So the רבנן rabbanan would
say we're afraid that if we let you use this rope, even
though in context it is very temporary, it looks like a regular
rope and it'll lead to people using regular rope, and רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda is not concerned. So that's a way of reframing the
debate, which again, none of that is in the משנה, mishnah, but
the גמרא Gemara feels a need to say that because or else
you can't explain how רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda could allow it. So
now the גמרא Gemara says למימרא, l'memra, so what you're telling me
is דרבנן סברי גזרינן חבל דגרדי אטו חבל דעלמא, drabbanan savri gazrinan
chevel d'garde atu chevel d'alma, we're afraid that a weaver's rope, if
we allow that, it will lead to using a normal rope. רבי
יהודה סבר לא גזרינן. Rebbe Yehuda savar lo gazrinan. Rebbe Yehuda would
say that we're not concerned, we don't think people will make that
mistake. ורמינהו, uremihu, I'll ask you on this, we've got the
following ברייתא. braita. חבל דלי שנפסק. chevel dli shenifsak. If you have
a rope of a bucket that broke, exactly our case in the
משנה, mishnah, but now what do you want to do? As opposed
to our משנה mishnah where you're bringing in the totally new rope,
the bucket might have been
unattached. Here you're trying to reconnect the rope. So you want to
basically tie the two ends of the rope back together. So what
do you do? לא יקשרנו אלא עונבו. lo yikshrenu ela ovno. Don't
knot it, make a slipknot. Okay. That's what the רבנן rabbanan say.
רבי יהודה אומר. Rebbe Yehuda omer. Rebbe Yehuda says כורך עליו פונדא
או פסקיא, korech alav punda o paskia,
you can tie upon it some type of a sash or belt
ובלבד שלא יענבנו, u-bilvad shelo ya'anveinu, but don't make a bow. Now
the statement of tie a belt works very well with the משנה
mishnah because we're saying Rebbe Yehuda allows in the משנה mishnah to
tie a rope and we just said that the rope that Rebbe
Yehuda would allow would be- well, actually everybody agrees in the משנה
mishnah that you can tie this type of a sash or belt.
won't be confused with a rope. Okay, so presumably, that statement of
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda of a sash or belt is not at
all debated. What is debated is whether you
can—is that—is that whether you can do a slipknot, where the rabbis
say yes, and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says no. So let's see
why the גמרא Gemara feels this is a problem.
קשיא דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה, Kashya de'Rebbe Yehuda ad'Rebbe Yehuda, רבי יהודה's
Rebbe Yehuda contradicting himself. קשיא דרבנן אדרבנן, Kashya de'Rabbanan ad'Rabbanan, the rabbis
are contradicting themselves. How are they contradicting themselves? Right, the idea of
a slipknot wasn't mentioned in the משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna just
discussed the sash, which everybody's saying is okay, said okay in the
משנה, Mishna, said okay here.
And so what does it have to do with the slipknot? So
the גמרא Gemara understands that here's the issue. The גמרא Gemara assumes
that everybody would say in principle a slipknot should totally be okay.
It's totally temporary, of course it should be okay. The question is,
is that will if we allow you to do a slipknot, will
you come to confuse it with a permanent knot? So, and we
just had in the משנה Mishna that the debate of רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda and the rabbis is do we let you use a
weaver's belt or are we afraid you'd be concerned you'd confuse that
with a normal belt. So the way we've set it up, רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is saying, 'I don't care, I'm not concerned that
you'll confuse one thing with another,' and the rabbis are saying, 'I
am concerned you'll confuse one thing with another.' So the rabbis are
concerned that you'll be confused, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is not. So
when it comes to the slipknot, how come it reverses? How come
the rabbis say don't use a slipknot and רבי יהודה—upside, Rebbe Yehuda
did I get it wrong? How come the rabbis say yes use
a slipknot and רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says don't use a slipknot?
Okay, so that's clear? We're abstracting that the whole issue is are
we afraid you'll be confused. But we assume that in principle everybody
would say a slipknot is okay. So how is it then that
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda, and the rabbis reversed their position? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: רבנן אדרבנן לא קשיא, Rabbanan ad'Rabbanan lo
kashya,
the rabbis on the rabbis is not difficult. חבל בחבל מיחלף, Chevel
be'chevel michlaf, one rope with another rope, people would be confused, it
all looks like a rope. עניבה בקשירה לא מיחלפא, Aniva be'kshira lo
michlafa, but a slipknot with a real knot, those are obviously different.
So yes, the rabbis are concerned about confusion in the rope case,
not in the slipknot case.
So you can borrow your rope, knowing that you have to give
it back to him, so you can still use a slip—yes, yes,
exactly.
Exactly. רבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה לא קשיא, Rebbe Yehuda ad'Rebbe Yehuda lo
kashya, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is not a contradiction. Why not? I
mean it's a good point, it's more likely to confuse one rope
with another than a slipknot with a regular knot. So here's why.
התם לא משום דמיחלפא עניבה בקשירה. Hasam lo mishum de'michlafa aniva be'kshira.
It's not because we're afraid that the slipknot will be confused with
a knot. You're right, that's less of a reason to be concerned
than one rope with another. אלא עניבה גופא קשירה היא. Ela aniva
gufa kshira hi.
He would say that a slipknot is actually a knot. It'll last
a long time. Yes, it's easy to undo, but it will last
a long time. Okay, so that's an interesting principle debate about a
slipknot. You can keep a slipknot for a very, very long time
even if it's very easy to undo. So now by the way,
I'll remind you that in the first משנה Mishna we had the
position of רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir that says if you can undo
it with one hand, it's not a problem. And the גמרא Gemara
says, is that just another way of saying light, or what would
he say about a slipknot? Okay, so the one reading of the
גמרא Gemara is that the whole point of רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir
would be to say that even if you had a very good
slipknot, if you could undo it with one hand, it's not a
problem. So then you would have רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, who normally
is the assumed בר פלוגתא bar plugta of רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda
saying a slipknot is okay, and רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda saying that
a slipknot is no good. So it sort of sets up that
possible way of reading that debate. We פוסקן pasken that a slipknot
is not a problem, but here it says that it might not
just be a question of mixing up, it might be because it
can be permanent, it can be left that way for a long
time even though easy to undo. I should say by the way,
there's a whole question about what do you do when you're throwing
out your garbage on שבת? Shabbos? I'm not talking about the מוקצה
muktzeh issue right now, although it's not not מוקצה muktzeh stuff, anyway,
whatever, we'll not talk about מוקצה, muktzeh, but you know, what do
you do, you sort of, how do you like tie the bag,
if you then got to like throw it out, wherever you're throwing
it out to. So
some people use the twist things, right? Because those are like, it's
not a knot and it's easy to undo, right? There's a question,
some people have a question that maybe if you twist it very
well, maybe that counts as a knot. Anyway, some people say, well,
if you do it with the bag itself, it's all going to
be מתקלקל, mitkalkel, it's all going to be destroyed. Anyway, what I
do is, if you want to know my great solution, is I
take the bag, I like to spin it, so you turn
the top part into really like almost like a string, and then
you just make a tight slipknot. And it's perfect. It stays really,
really tight because you know, even if it pulls, it really just
tightens the knot, but it's a slipknot, so it's not a problem.
Yes.
So regarding the other day when we were talking about קשר אומנים
kesher umanim and all of that, apparently this is all thrown out
the window now, because I know this is a קשר אומנים, kesher
umanim, it's not—no, what do you mean?
This is a—well, first of all, even when רבי יהודה says it's
no good, are you talking about if the slipknot is no good?
So again, according to רש"י, Rashi, it's not about קשר אומנים, kesher
umanim, it's about permanence. So it's an interesting question, something that might
be left there permanently, although it is true something that is made
as a slipknot certainly not for the purpose of being permanent, it's
to have the ability to undo it. But anyway, we're here probably
talking totally within a דרבנן d'rabbanan category, there's no indication that we're
talking דאורייתא, d'oraisa, we're just talking מותר muttar or אסור, assur, so
we're within the דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב, Amar Rabbi
Abba, Amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Ashi, Amar Rav, מביא אדם חבל מתוך
ביתו. mivi adam chevel mitokh beito. אמר רבי אבא אמר רבי חייא
בר אשי אמר רב מביא אדם חבל מתוך ביתו וקושרו בפרה ובאבוס.
Amar Rabi Abba amar Rabi Chiyah bar Ashi amar Rav mevi adam
chevel m’toch beiso v’koshro b’parah u’va’eivus. That you can go ahead on
שבת. Shabbos. It’s amazing like by this thing, I mean, you know,
the types of things it’s describing besides the knot, it just feels
meaty to me, very like עובדא דחול, uvda d’chol, you know, because
of like when it talks about the rope in front of your
animals in the pen. Here it says you take a rope and
you tie it one end to the, you know, to the cow,
to like the collar around the cow, one end to the, to
the, what's it called, to the like trough, and and that's fine.
We're not afraid that you'll, that after it’s done you'll leave it
that way, you'll free, we'll assume you'll free both ends. Okay, but
even besides the knot thing, it’s like, what? You’re tying your cow
to the trough on שבת? Shabbos? Is that appropriate? But you know,
you know, if you live in this, in that world, obviously we
live in a very different world, but that, if you live in
that world, you know, that is a sort of regular thing that
needs to be attended to.
But here’s a חבל, chevel, you can do it.
And it's a, right, and it's a חבל chevel and you can
do it because we know you're not going to leave your cow
attached to attached. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
איתיבי רב אחא אריכא רב אחא דהוא רבי אחא בר פפא, Eisvei
Rav Acha Aricha Rav Acha d’hu Rabi Acha bar Pappa, one asked,
I know, we had another tall one before, רבי אבא, Rabi Abba,
he asked רבי אבא. Rabi Abba. חבל שבאיבוס, Chevel she’ba’eivus, the, here
the ברייתא, Baraisa, it says the rope on the trough, קושרו בפרה,
koshro b’parah, you can tie it to the cow. I mean, if
it was pre-tied to the trough, you can tie the other end
to the cow. ושבפרה קושרו באיבוס, V’she’b’parah koshro b’eivus, and on the,
if it’s pre-tied to the cow, you can tie it to the
trough. ובלבד שלא יביא חבל מתוך ביתו ויקשור בפרה ובאיבוס, U’vilvad shelo
yavi chevel m’toch beiso v’yikshor b’parah u’va’eivus, but you can’t tie both
ends. Why can’t you tie both ends? Because then when you’re done,
you might only untie one of them. You won’t necessarily untie both,
you don’t need to untie both. So at least one of them
will be a permanent knot. So you see there and it makes
a lot of sense and it contradicts what you said. So he
says, you’re right. התם חבל דעלמא, Hasam chevel d’alma, that’s a normal
rope. So a normal rope, just like by the bucket, we’re afraid
that you’ll leave one end attached. הכא חבל דגרדי, Hacha chevel d’gardi,
here we’d be talking like we said what רבי יהודה's case was,
we’d be talking about a weaver's belt. So therefore when you’re done,
you’re not going to leave the belt there, you need to give
it back to the weaver, you need to use it for your
whatever professional use. So it's just like our משנה Mishna about the
bucket. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, so
they're going to name in שמואל. Shmuel. כל כלי קיבואי מותר לטלטלו
בשבת. Kol k’lei kivoi mutar l’taltalo b’Shabbos. All, I'm sorry, כלי, k’lei,
excuse me, כלי, k’lei, excuse me, כלי קיבואי, k’lei kivoi,
is מותר mutar to carry on שבת. Shabbos. So רש"י Rashi says
that that basically is a we all weavers' sort of vessels. So
really because we're talking about a weaver's belt, we're talking we're moving
on to not talking about knotting but about מוקצה. muktzah. So all
of the various instruments that are used by the weaver, you're allowed
to carry on שבת, Shabbos, we’re not afraid they’re מוקצה. muktzah. Now
what type of מוקצה muktzah might they be? So you know רש"י
Rashi says whether it’s מלאכתו לאיסור, melachto l’issur, but actually they are
מלאכתו לאיסור. melachto l’issur. רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi seems to sometimes like
use some of the terms that we have for מוקצה, muktzah, I
think I would say either like imprecisely or not in the same
way we use them. Okay, the the the
here presumably these are מלאכתו לאיסור, melachto l’issur, but it’s not a
problem because you can move a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור k’lei she’melachto l’issur
if you're moving it for its own sake, just as you know,
if you’re moving it לצורך
גופו או לצורך מקומו. l’tzorech gufo o l’tzorech mekomo. You need the
space, you need to use it. The only thing you can't move
it for is to protect it from damage, okay, מחמה לצל. me’chamah
l’tzel. But the issue here is maybe not just is it מלאכתו
לאיסור, melachto l’issur, maybe it's like so valuable or so delicate that
you basically don't want somebody to touch it at all. That would
make it like a, you know, מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס, muktzah machmas
chisron kis, like, you know, you know, so something that you don't
want anybody to be touching or fiddling with, and that you could
wouldn’t be able to move for any purpose. So the גמרא Gemara
is saying that’s not an issue. You’re allowed to move these various
these various instruments of the weaver. בעי מיניה מרב יהודה, Ba’ei minei
mi’Rav Yehuda, they asked רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. כובד עליון וכובד תחתון
מהו? Koved elyon v’koved tachton mahu? How about, I think they have
a nice picture here in the in the in the שטיינזלץ. Steinsaltz.
Do they? Yeah,
could you, I don’t know, could you show that? Or,
yeah, is this also one? That's that's the wrong volume.
It's not in that one. It's right there.
Yeah, thank you.
So, right.
Yeah, it really helps to have seen a real loom at some
point.
So anyway, it's got if you see here, it's got an upper
and a lower beam. And that's the כובד עליון וכובד תחתון, koved
elyon v’koved tachton, okay? So here you see they make the whole
thing on this on this whole loom, right, and it’s going in
both. So anyway, it's got an upper and a lower beam, okay?
So that's the question about what about those? Maybe those really are,
you know, those aren't just like the rope or some type of
a small little instrument, you know, that's actually part of this whole
major structure of the frame. Maybe that is something you can't move.
Maybe that's like מוקצה מחמת חסרון כיס. muktzah machmas chisron kis.
So, let's take a look.
אים ולאו ורפיה בידיה. Im v’lav v’rafya b’yadei. He said yeah, no,
yeah, no, he and he would be weak in his hand, he
wouldn't really know how to answer that. איתמר, Ismar, was taught, אמר
רב נחמן אמר שמואל, amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel, כלי קיבואי מותר
לטלטלו בשבת, k’lei kivoi mutar l’taltalo b’Shabbos, you can you can move
them, אפילו כובד עליון וכובד תחתון, afilu koved elyon v’koved tachton, even
the upper and lower beam, אבל לא את העמודים. aval lo es
ha’amudim. That’s the sort of horizontal beams but not like the, not
like the frame itself. Not like the vertical beams that are actually
stuck into the ground. That not. So the גמרא Gemara is trying
to understand why that's different. אמרי ליה רבא לרב נחמן, amrei leh
Rava l'Rav Nachman, מאי שנא עמודים דלא? mai shna amudim delo? Why
not the vertical beams? Of אי אילימא i ileima משום גומות mishum
gumot because if you take them out of the ground you'll make
a little hole in the ground? גומות ממילא קא הוו, gumot mimeila
ka'avin, that's incidental, you're not intending,
and ותנן, v't'nan, actually you say the holes are already made, but
maybe you know you'll make them a little deeper as you're digging
them out of the ground. ותנן, v't'nan, we taught in the משנה,
Mishna, הטומן לפת וצנונות תחת הגפן, hatomen lefet v'tznonot tachat hagefen, if
somebody buries
like a radish or a
turnip
under a vine, right? These are already detached from the ground, but
you're just burying them in the earth. Okay, אם מקצת עליו מגולין,
im miktzat alav megulin, if some of the leaves are exposed,
אינו חושש eino choshesh לא משום כלאים ולא משום שביעית. lo mishum
kilayim v'lo mishum shvi'is. Now רש״י Rashi says the leaves being exposed
is only mentioned for the שבת Shabbat purpose. Whether the leaves are
exposed or not, they're not really growing, they've just been replanted. Although
I don't know, some of these root vegetables if you replant them
will they begin to take root again? Yes. Yeah, so that's real,
so
it is really a pretty big חידוש, chiddush, but anyway you don't
have to be concerned about כלאים, kilayim, about the fact that now
you have another plant growing near your vine, or שמיטה shmita if
it's a שמיטה shmita year that now it has קדושת שביעית, kedushas
shvi'is, ולא משום מעשר v'lo mishum ma'aser or if you already took
מעשר ma'aser on it, you don't have to be concerned that it
grew more and you have to take מעשר ma'aser again on it,
okay? Because these have already been caught, they're just being re-buried in
the earth. And what's relevant for us is
וניטלין בשבת, v'nitlin b'Shabbos, that you can take them on שבת, Shabbat,
even though in the act of, if it wasn't didn't have an
exposed leaf, you couldn't take it because you'd have to move directly
move the dirt and it would be a מוקצה muktzeh problem. But
because it has an exposed leaf, you grab the leaf, you pull
it out, and the fact that the dirt moves incidentally or the
fact that the hole is made incidentally is not a problem. It
was already in the hole. So he's saying the same thing is
true here. So the גמרא Gemara says why should it be a
problem? So the גמרא Gemara says בשדה לא אתי לאשויי גומות. b'sadeh
lo asu l'ashvuyei gumos. Yeah, that's in the field, just because it's
a hole you're not going to come to smooth over the hole.
הכא בבית, hacha b'bayis, here we're talking about in your house, אתי
לאשויי גומות. asu l'ashvuyei gumos. You don't want a hole in the
floor in your house. So we're not concerned that you'll make a
hole, we're concerned once you have an exposed hole you'll come to
smooth over it. And that will be a type of at least
דרבנן de-rabanan if not worse, of a type of בונה boneh that
you'll try to fill in the hole. Okay, so that's the concern,
not a מוקצה muktzeh concern. בעי מיניה רבי יוחנן מרבי יהודה בר
ליוואי, ba'i minei Rabbi Yochanan me-Rabbi Yehuda bar Livai, so Rabbi Yochanan
asked Rabbi
Yehuda bar Livai, כלי קיבלי כגון כובדא עליונה וכובדא תחתונה, klei kibli
kegon koveda elayna v'koveda tachtona, מהו לטלטלן בשבת? mahu letaltelan b'Shabbat? Same
question. How about moving not just the weavers' like sort of more
movable things, but how about even moving the upper and lower post,
horizontal post? אמר ליה, amar leh, אין מטלטלין, ein metalpelin, you can't
move them. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why not? לפי שאין ניטלין, l'fi
she'ein nitlin, because you can't move them. Okay, like I said, you
can't move. No, but that's not what he said. Actually he didn't
say, he said לפי שאין ניטלין l'fi she'ein nitlin which means because
not because I'm saying you're not allowed to, but he's saying because
they are not moved. And רש״י Rashi says this means since they
are not usually moved, usually you never you leave them in that
place and you don't want to move them anywhere else, that makes
it a מוקצה, muktzeh, essentially it's a type of מוקצה מחמת חסרון
כיס. muktzeh machmas chisron kis. One of the basic definitions of מוקצה
מחמת חסרון כיס muktzeh machmas chisron kis is something that you don't
ever want to move because you're afraid it's delicate, it'll be damaged.
You've got a vase up on your mantle, nobody's ever supposed to
touch it, you don't want it to be damaged, you don't want
it to be moved. That is a type of a מוקצה muktzeh
and that is what he is saying here. Okay, so that was
a little digression. Moving on to the next משנה. mishna.
מקפלין את הכלים. mekaplin es hakelim. Now we are as I said,
although we are dealing with דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, you know we dealt with
אלו קשרים, elu ksharim, the whole previous thing was about was about
was you know was חבלה chabala and צידה. tzeida. We also are
along the way getting much more into practical issues. דרבנן de-rabanan of
the דאורייתא de-Oraisa like what type of knots are rabbinically forbidden. But
not only that, we are going to start as you see with
a lot of משניות mishnaot that don't have a reference to particularly
what מלאכה melacha we're talking about, but just talk about things that
are rabbinically a problem like we had a whole discussion about the
types of medications you can take. By the way, the גמרא Gemara
I should point out, not only did the משנה mishna not mention
that it was related to this concern of grinding, the גמרא, Gemara,
that גמרא Gemara we did never mentioned that. It's another גמרא Gemara
that said it's based on a concern of grinding and actually it's
only the גמרא Gemara that says, there's possibly you know there's other
ways of understanding that maybe it was you know it wasn't based
on a concern of grinding, it was concern of something else. But
my point being that the משניות, mishnaot, a lot of the משניות
mishnaot in this vicinity and really till the end are going to
talk about don't do this, you can do this, you can't do
this, you don't do this, and it sounds like we're not talking
necessarily about a דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, not even it's clear if it's a
reference to a דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, maybe there's some other concern. Okay, so
let's take a look at this משנה. mishna. מקפלין את הכלים, mekaplin
es hakelim, you can fold your garments on שבת, Shabbat, אפילו ארבעה
וחמישה פעמים, afilu arba v'chamisha p'amim, even four or five times, ומציעין
את המיטות, u-matzi'in es hamittos, and you can also make the beds,
like lay out the... And the sheets on the bed, מלילי שבת
לשבת, milelei Shabbos l’Shabbos, from Friday night if for the sake of
שבת, Shabbos, like you’re going to sleep on the bed on שבת,
Shabbos, אבל לא משבת למוצאי שבת, aval lo mi-Shabbos l’motzei Shabbos, you
can't make the bed on שבת Shabbos for Saturday night. רבי ישמעאל
אומר, Reb Yishmael omer, רבי ישמעאל Reb Yishmael says, מקפלין את הכלים
ומציעין את המיטות mekaplin et hakelim u-matzi’in et hamitot מיום כיפור לשבת.
mi-Yom Kippur l’Shabbos. You can't do it maybe for מוצאי שבת, motzei
Shabbos, but you can do it from יום כיפור Yom Kippur to
שבת Shabbos because יום כיפור Yom Kippur is maybe one, well you
would say maybe one קדושה kedusha with שבת, Shabbos, meaning let’s say
יום כיפור Yom Kippur fell out on a Friday, but actually we’re
going to see it’s a slightly lower קדושה kedusha so it can
serve שבת. Shabbat. וחלבי שבת, Ve-chelvei Shabbos, wait one minute because I
want to confirm after יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. This is שבת Shabbat
after יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. יום כיפור Yom Kippur was a Friday.
Yeah, before they established the calendar.
Okay. וחלבי שבת קרבים ביום הכיפורים. Ve-chelvei Shabbos krevim be-Yom HaKippurim. And
if it’s the reverse, יום כיפור Yom Kippur is a Sunday, so
you brought a קרבן korban on שבת, Shabbos, you can burn the
fats מוצאי שבת motzei Shabbos on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So in
both of those scenarios, יום כיפור Yom Kippur is essentially serving שבת.
Shabbos. אבל לא של יום כיפור בשבת. Aval lo shel Yom Kippur
be-Shabbos. But let's say it was, let's say יום כיפור Yom Kippur
was Friday, you can't burn the fats of the קרבנות korbanot of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur on שבת Shabbos because שבת Shabbos doesn't serve
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. רבי עקיבא אומר לא של שבת קרבים ביום
הכיפורים ולא של יום כיפור קרבים בשבת. Rabbi Akiva omer lo shel
Shabbos krevim be-Yom Kippurim ve-lo shel Yom Kippur krevim be-Shabbos. No, they
can't serve one another, each one can only be done for the
day itself, not for a previous day, not for a following day.
So what is the concern of the משנה? Mishna? This משנה Mishna
seems to be a concern of what we would call, well, we
won’t worry about the דאורייתות de-oraitas of like burning fats, okay, because
that’s a real question about doing a מלאכה melacha on one day
for the next, but the idea of folding your garment or making
your bed is not a מלאכה. melacha. So this משנה Mishna seems
to be what the concern we call as הכנה, hachana, preparing from
one day to the next. And this as I said, here we
are, we’re talking about different מלאכות, melachas, קשר, kesher, צידה, tzeidah, חבלה,
chabala, and in the middle we’re just throwing in here’s other things
you can or can’t do on שבת, Shabbos, here’s a new concern,
a concern of הכנה. hachana. Now we normally frame it as הכנה,
hachana, and that leads to certain questions like, you know, am I
allowed to study on שבת Shabbos for the test I have on
Sunday, okay, or whatever, or Monday, but still it’s a whatever, I
need to study from now until the test. It’s interesting to note
that some of the ראשונים Rishonim don't frame the איסור issur as
an איסור issur of הכנה, hachana, they frame the איסור issur as
טורח בשבת לצורך חול, tore'ach be-Shabbos le-tzorech chol, which is to sort
of expend effort on שבת. Shabbos. So but when you frame it
as טורח, tore'ach, it, you know, it somehow reframes it a little
bit. It's not like anything that is done, you know, how about
if I’m allowed to think today, you know, about what I’m planning
to do on מוצאי שבת? motzei Shabbos? Am I allowed to talk?
Actually we’re going to talk in a minute about talking about מוצאי
שבת, motzei Shabbos, but that’s more of an issue of דובר דבר,
dover davar, about weekday talk on שבת, Shabbos, it’s not an issue
of הכנה. hachana. Okay, so it is a question about what types
of things are in this הכנה hachana and some ראשונים Rishonim do
very much frame it as טורח בשבת לצורך חול. tore'ach be-Shabbos le-tzorech
chol. That seems to be the focus on the משנה Mishna about
folding your garment for after שבת, Shabbos, making your bed for after
שבת. Shabbos. Now we'll talk about this in a minute in the
גמרא, Gemara, but I do want to say that there's a very
important qualification to this, which is, you know, very often your things
are ready for the next day but that's not the immediate reason
you're doing it. And this is like a big, I think, mistake,
right, there's a big, I think, over חומרא over-chumra that some people
have on שבת Shabbos like, like let's say you have a
סעודה שלישית seudah shelishit and it's over and whatever, it's like, you
know, it's still not צאת הכוכבים, tzeit hachokhavim, so people say, what,
you can't clean it up because it's like getting it ready for
מוצאי שבת. motzei Shabbos. So it's not getting it ready for מוצאי
שבת. motzei Shabbos. Like I don't, I don't like even for two
minutes there to be a messy dining room here, you know, to
be all this crumbs, all this mess, right? So it has nothing
to do with מוצאי שבת. motzei Shabbos. It's right now I don't
like the mess. Why? You get out of bed in the morning,
you make the bed so that it’ll be nice at night, or
you make the bed because you want your bedroom to look nice
after you get out of the bed, right? So that I, so
basically so the פוסקים poskim say definitely, although in terms of people's
feeling it's okay to do this, I've seen a shift, you know,
that at least I grew up or it seems like everybody felt
like, you know, at least if it's possible it's for מוצאי שבת
motzei Shabbos it's אסור, assur, whereas now I see much more פוסקים
poskim are saying, the משנה ברורה Mishna Berura already says it, but
I see even in some of these contemporary books פוסקים poskim much
more saying like, no, if you just don't like a dirty dining
room table, if you don't like, you know, when I put my
garbage in the garbage bag, it's not because I'm getting it ready
to throw out on מוצאי שבת, motzei Shabbos, it's because, you know,
I don't like the stuff around. If I want to make my
bed, if I want to clean the room because that's the way
I want it to look, then I'm not doing it לצורך מחר,
le-tzorech machar, I'm doing it לצורך עכשיו. le-tzorech achshav. Okay, so that's
important as a distinction. I once was מחמיר machmir when
I, when we finished a bottle of whatever of soda, you know,
so what you do is you like rinse it out, rinse it
out and put it in the recycling. So I didn't want to
do that on שבת Shabbos because I said that was like הכנה,
hachana, you know, somehow getting it ready to be thrown out מוצאי
שבת, motzei Shabbos, but then I said, no, it's not הכנה, hachana,
it's like that's what you do with, you know, that's where you
put, that's what you do with your bottles, you rinse them and
put them there, that's where they belong, you know? That's, so it's
not like, and that's true, in your mindset you're not thinking, oh...
do this so I'll be able to put it in recycling מוצאי
שבת. Motzei Shabbos. Like, that's what you do with the stuff in
your house, that's how you put it away and take care of
it. So with that in mind, it's interesting the issue of folding
because
when you fold your clothes, you're not folding them so they'll be
ready for after שבת. Shabbos. You fold your clothes so that they
don't get wrinkled. So that's the way you put them away is
that you fold them, so you treat them nicely. So actually the
ערוך השולחן Aruch HaShulchan does say this, that that's okay, if you're
basically doing it because it's basically because just you don't want it
to get wrinkled, how you want to put it away, but it
is interesting how some people will be very מחמיר machmir on the
folding. As we do the גמרא, Gemara, we're going to read another
problem with the folding. But again, the same principle would apply. I'll
mention one other example about this is about bringing your טלית tallis
home. You take your טלית tallis to שול, shul, and let's say
you don't have a box in שול shul to keep it in
or whatever, and now can you take it home? So there are
some people that are very מחמיר. machmir. Yep, can't take it home,
it's לצורך מחר. letzorech machar. I'm not going to need my טלית
tallis until Sunday. So I'm doing it לצורך מחר. letzorech machar. But
give me a break, you're not doing it לצורך מחר. letzorech machar.
You don't want to leave your טלית tallis in שול. shul. It's
going to get lost, who knows what's going to happen. So just
because the reality is you're not going to leave it until tomorrow
and by being at home it'll be available to you tomorrow, doesn't
mean that you're doing it as a הכנה hachanah for tomorrow. You're
doing it because you want your שבת Shabbos טלית tallis at home,
you don't want it to be left in שול. shul. So it
is interesting that that is actually explicitly stated that that's okay, but
how people go a little bit overboard with that. So now we're
going to look at the גמרא Gemara and see the issue about
folding. The גמרא Gemara introduces a new problem with folding.
By the way, if you want to see an example of that,
look at תוספות Tosafot מכפלין. Mechaphlin. תוספות Tosafot says כלים. Keilim. He
says מכאן למדנו דאסור לקפל טליתות של בית הכנסת לפי שאין צורך
מחר. Mikan lamadnu de'assur lekappel tallitot shel beit haknesset lephi she'ein tzorech
machar.
So again, if you're doing it not just so it looks nice
tomorrow, but if you're doing it so that again, it doesn't get
wrinkled and it stays nice, then it wouldn't be a problem, but
תוספות Tosafot sort of puts it out there and that leads to
some way of thinking that it doesn't matter, it's always אסור assur
because you're not going to use it until tomorrow.
So two things. One is getting back to the tying and tallis
also. When you have a tie and tallis knot,
it just becomes a little bit loose. So tightening that, is that,
we're going to understand this as a סוג של קושר? sug shel
kosher? Right? Even though it was kind of like that again and
it will come out later. So that's one thing. So why is
that? And the other is about טליתות. tallitot. As far as I
understood, and with anything, there's an issue about folding it along the
original fold.
Alright, so that second part we're going to talk about. The first
part is I'm not going to get to. That's הלכה למעשה. halacha
l'maaseh. We'll talk about that later.
אמר דבי רבי ינאי, Amar d'bei Rabbi Yannai, in the house of
Rabbi Yannai. לא שנו אלא באדם אחד. Lo shanu ela b'adam echad.
When is it מותר mutar to fold a טלית, tallis, whatever, your
clothes multiple times? Again, assuming you're going to use it on the
same day, or what I just explained, assuming you're doing it, not
for הכנה hachanah but just to keep it nice. When is that
allowed? With one person. אבל בשני בני אדם לא, Aval b'shnei bnei
adam lo, with two people, לא, lo, you can't do it. Now
why not? What's the problem? So if you take a look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says כשהם מקפלין אותן מפשטין קמטיהן ונראים כמתקנין.
Keshehem mekapplin otan mafashtin kimteihen venirim kemetakenin. That when you
fold it in a particular way, like in a very precise way,
then it's not just that you're putting it away nicely, it's like
you're smoothing it out and you're smoothing out all the wrinkles. The
example I give is like some people if you see them hanging
up their pants,
the way they are so מקפיד makpid to do it exactly on
the crease, right, and they make it exactly precise and everything is
smoothed out. So that is seen like you're not just preserving it,
like you're actually fixing it, like you're making it, you're making it
better, you're removing
the creases, you're keeping the crease in the leg. So that's the
problem. ונראה כמתקן. Venira kemetaken. It looks like you're fixing.
Just something's big and needs two people then that looks like, yeah,
exactly.
Okay, but not like folding a tablecloth. אבל בשני בני אדם לא.
Aval b'shnei bnei adam lo. ובאדם אחד נמי לא אמרן אלא בחדשים.
U'b’adam echad nami lo amran ela b’chadashim. Only new ones, which it
doesn't look so much like you're fixing them. אבל
בישנים, Aval b’yeshanim, in old ones, where it looks more like they
need, like they're more crinkled and they need more to be fixed,
לא, lo, you can't. והחדשים נמי לא אמרן אלא בלבנים. Ve'hachadashim nami
lo amran ela b'levanim. Only white ones. אבל בצבועים, Aval b'tzvuyim, in
colored ones, maybe there where, I don't know, either the material would
be different or somehow people would be more exacting on its folds,
לא, lo, it's not good. ולא אמרן אלא שאין לו להחליף. Ve'lo
amran ela she'ein lo lehachalif. And even when we allowed it with
one person in all these things, one person, new, white ones, it's
almost totally אסור assur now, right? Even that is only when you
have no other garment. אבל יש לו להחליף, Aval yesh lo lehachalif,
if you have another garment, לא, lo, then you can't do it
because then if you have another one, then you're not doing it
for today, you're doing it for tomorrow. That gets back to the
other idea of הכנה, hachanah, not the idea of fixing. But so
right, because if you have another one, you don't need it for
later today, so the whole thing is for tomorrow, so it's also
אסור. assur. So here you have this גמרא Gemara coming... another garment,
לא, lo, then you can't do it because then if you have
another one, then you're not doing it for today, you're doing it
for tomorrow, that gets back to the other idea of הכנה, hachana,
not the idea of fixing. But so right, because if you have
another one, you don't need it for later today, so the whole
thing is for tomorrow, so it's also אסור. assur. So here you
have this גמרא gemara coming out, seems to come out of left
field, that all of a sudden said even when it's not a
הכנה hachana issue, there's a fundamental problem about folding, that folding is
like fixing. And you actually will see people, I see it quite
often in שול, shul, that people are putting away a טלית, tallis,
doing basically what they'll do is they'll fold it—they either just roll
it up and shove it in, or they fold it like reverse,
not on its natural fold, but like inside out of its natural
fold, because of this גמרא. gemara.
But a lot of people aren't מקפיד makpid on that, and it
seems like a very strange concern. And the ערוך השולחן Aruch HaShulchan
basically says—he says, yeah, everybody folds their stuff, it's not a problem.
He says this גמרא gemara is talking about a very specific type
of way of, like I said, like folding it extremely precisely, like
imagine like going down the crease of the pants leg, doing it
like multiple times so that the crease really gets shaped and gets
preserved, and that's like a נראה כמתקן. nireh kemetaken. And a normal
folding that you do on the natural folds to keep the garment
from getting wrinkled is not a problem; you're just putting it away.
And again, if you're doing it to preserve it from wrinkles, it's
also not a הכנה hachana issue. But there are people that are
very מקפיד makpid on that with their טלית tallis and other things
based on this גמרא. gemara.
So what you're saying is you don't really have to worry about
that.
Yeah, as long as you're not
like sharpening the crease and really laying it flat and getting out
the wrinkles and something like this, you're just folding it on its
natural folds.
And with your pants, do the same
thing.
Yeah. Yeah. Yes. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says, תנא דבי
רבן גמליאל: tana devei Rabban Gamliel: they taught in the house of
רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, which was wealthy, לא היו מקפלין כלי לבן
שלהן: lo hayu mekappelin klei lavan shelahen: even the white ones, they
would not do, מפני שהיה להן להחליף: mipnei shehaya lahen lehachalif: even
though otherwise it would be okay, מפני שהיה להן להחליף: mipnei shehaya
lahen lehachalif: they had other garments to switch into, so it would
then become a הכנה hachana issue, assuming that that's defined as הכנה.
hachana. Okay. אמר רב הונא: amar Rav Huna: אם יש לו להחליף
יחליף. im yesh lo lehachalif yachalif. Now because we're talking about switching
clothes and שבת Shabbos and this and that, now the גמרא gemara
is going to have a very fascinating digression, maybe not such a
digression because it ties into the issue of sort of the whole
sense of הכנה, hachana, but we're going to talk about כבוד שבת
kevod Shabbos now, various aspects of כבוד שבת. kevod Shabbos. If you
have garments to change into—different garments to wear on שבת—you Shabbos should
wear special garments on שבת. Shabbos. You should have שבת Shabbos clothes.
ואם אין לו להחליף, ve'im ein lo lehachalif, if you don't have
a second set of clothes to wear, special clothes for
שבת, Shabbos, ישלשל, yeshalshel, then what you should do is you should
sort of lower your—like if they had some type of a skirt
or whatever, lower it down a little bit so that the hem
goes closer to the ground. And that makes it look like more
people that have to work, you can't have the hem of your
clothes too close to the ground. So if it's very close to
the ground, that sort of is more of a sign of wealth
or leisure and therefore, even though it's the same garment, it looks
more appropriate for שבת. Shabbos. So the גמרא gemara says: אמר רב
הונא—I'm amar Rav Huna sorry, I just did
that—ישלשל בבגדיו. yeshalshel bevagdav.
So מתקיף לה רב ספרא: matkif lah Rav Safra: רב ספרא Rav
Safra asks: והא מיתחזי כרמות רוחא? veha mitchazi keramut rucha? It looks
arrogant walking around with this, with these the hem right next to
the ground; it's like these
wealthy, arrogant look. So the גמרא gemara says: No, כיון דכל יומא
לא קעביד, keivan dechol yoma lo ka'avid, since you normally don't do
that, והאידנא הוא דקעביד, ve'ha'idna hu deka'avid, you're just doing it now
for שבת, Shabbos, לא מיתחזי כרמות רוחא, lo mitchazi keramut rucha, it
doesn't look like that. Okay. וכבדתו מעשות דרכיך, vechibadto measot derachecha, you
should honor it, the שבת, Shabbos, from doing your normal ways. So
what does that mean? וכבדתו, vechibadto, so we're going to make a
דרשה drasha on that פסוק, pasuk, although it's from the נביאים, nevi'im,
from
ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. וכבדתו, vechibadto, you should honor it, שלא יהא מלבושך של
שבת כמלבושך של חול, shelo yehei malbushecha shel Shabbos kemalbushecha shel chol,
you should not—the way you honor something,
the way you show honor is very often defined by the way
you dress. So the way you dress on שבת Shabbos should not
be the way you dress during the weekday. וכי הא דרבי יוחנן,
vechi ha deRabbi Yochanan, like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, קרי למאני מכבדותי.
kari lemanei mechabduyotai. He called his garments "the things that give me
honor." So you sort of treat yourself with respect when you dress
nicely,
and therefore the same way your clothes are a sign of the
respect you're showing for yourself, they also are a sign for the
respect that they show for the environment, for the day, for שבת.
Shabbos. Okay, so that's that דרשה. drasha. I have to tell you
that
wearing a suit and a tie every single day, it's like: what
do I wear special for שבת? Shabbos? So
some people wear more relaxed clothes on שבת, Shabbos, but I don't
think that that's the—that might be עונג שבת, oneg Shabbos, it's not
כבוד שבת, kevod Shabbos, right? I actually knew a guy that—a rabbi
who, like he would come home from שול, shul, he would have
a suit and tie on, he'd make קידוש, Kiddush, he'd say, "Okay,
that's כבוד שבת." kevod Shabbos. Then he would take off his tie
and say, "Now it's time for
עונג שבת." oneg Shabbos. Right? Anyway, but—so I try to have some
of my nicer suits that I only wear on שבת. Shabbos. And
the other thing that I've started doing is that I wear my
French cuff shirts on שבת Shabbos and not during the weekday. So
but it's interesting, like: how do you know, what—how do you make
sure you have special garments for שבת? Shabbos? Okay, anyway, it goes
on.
מעשות דרכיך, measot derachecha, you should not do your normal ways. שלא
יהא הילוכך של שבת כהילוכך של חול. shelo yehei hiluchecha shel Shabbos
ke'hiluchecha shel chol. so you shouldn't- your going, your literally your walking
on שבת Shabbos should not be like your walking on the weekday.
we're going to unpack that in a minute. ממצוא חפצך mimzo cheftzecha
from
pursuing your desires. חפצך אסורין cheftzecha asurin your desires are forbidden. חפצי
שמים מותרין cheftzei Shamayim mutarin you can do it right for חפצי
שמים. cheftzei Shamayim. so חפצך cheftzecha is like and this again is
sort of connected to the הכנה hachana idea but not with טירחא.
tircha. like the גמרא Gemara says you cannot let's say walk over
to where your fields are and not say a word, you didn't-
all you did is you just took a walk but you're walking
over to where your fields are and you're inspecting them or looking
at them or you're there so you'll be ready to go to
them on מוצאי שבת. Motzoei Shabbos. that's ממצוא חפצך. mimzo cheftzecha. the
חפצי שמים cheftzei Shamayim are מותר muttar which has a lot to
do with why we can make various announcements after שול shul is
over because all of that is like in the sake of חפצי
שמים cheftzei Shamayim or talking about another example is talking about hiring
somebody, hiring somebody to be like a teacher for, you know, a
teacher for your kids. so that would be חפצי שמים cheftzei Shamayim
לצורך מצוה. l'tzorech mitzvah. okay those types of things are allowed even
though they're about, they involve things that you cannot do, they're about
preparing for after שבת Shabbos or they involve things you can't do
on שבת, Shabbos, that is allowed. this is חפצי שמים cheftzei Shamayim
not חפצך. chafatzecha.
you don't have to wear different
clothes- no no.
ודבר דבר V'daber davar speaking your normal speech, שלא יהא דיבורך של
שבת כדיבורך של חול shelo yehei diburcha shel Shabbos k'diburcha shel chol
you shouldn't speak on שבת Shabbos like you speak on the weekday.
now what does that mean? so if you look at רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says כגון מקח וממכר וחשבונות. k'gon mekach u'mimkar v'cheshbonos. you
don't start talking about the stock market, you don't talk about your
business, you don't talk weekday talk on שבת. Shabbos. okay so if
it's about actually planning things that would be more of a ממצוא
חפצך. mimzo cheftzecha. you're actually sort of pursuing your pursuit. but if
it's not about planning, it's just about what do you שמוז shmooze
about? are you שמוזינג shmooze-ing about your business? are you שמוזינג shmooze-ing
about that type of thing? that's also a weekday type of a
talk. תוספות Tosafot brings a very interesting ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. תוספות Tosafot says
פירש בקונטרס כגון מקח וממכר ואין נראה לרבינו תם דהא כבר נפקא
מממצוא חפצך. perish b'kuntres k'gon mekach u'mimkar v'ein nireh l'Rabbeinu Tam d'ha
kvar nafka mimimzo cheftzecha. that's already from ממצוא חפצך. mimzo cheftzecha. now
not necessarily, as I said ממצוא חפצך mimzo cheftzecha is actually like
a type of a pursuing a certain thing. like you're figuring out
how am I going to invest, what am I going to do
when I get back to the work to the office etc. there's
another category which is a שמוזינג shmooze-ing about it even though it's
not even, you know, pursuing it. but anyway תוספות Tosafot is bothered.
so תוספות Tosafot says אלא אמר רבינו תם כדאמר בויקרא רבה ר'
שמעון בן יוחאי הוה ליה אימא סבתא ela amar Rabbeinu Tam k'd'amar
b'Vayikra Rabba Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai havah lei ima savta he had
an older mother דהוות משתעי סגיא d'havat mishta'ei sagi she was talking
a lot on שבת. Shabbos. אמר לה אימא שבתא הוא amar lah
ima Shabbata hu he said to her,
mother it's שבת. Shabbos. שתקה shatka she was quiet. משמע mashma it
sounds from there שאין כל כך לדבר בשבת כמו בחול. she'ein kol
kach l'daber b'Shabbos k'mo b'chol.
you just shouldn't be as generally as talkative on שבת. Shabbos. okay?
ובירושלמי אמרינן בטורח התירו בשאילת שלום בשבת. u'v'Yerushalmi amrinan b'torach hitiru b'she'ilat
shalom b'Shabbos. so there is a there is some people say אדרבה
aderaba that's what's so nice about שבת Shabbos you can relax and
talk but there was a there was an attitude out there which
is mostly absent in חז"ל Chazal but actually I think it's somewhat
seen in some of the other sects, some of the sects from
the time of the בית שני Bayis Sheni period that one of
the natures of שבת Shabbos was quiet. that was very part of
the definition of שבת. Shabbos. like the opposite of the weekday is
quiet. so and that was something that was tried to be preserved.
like there's a I think there's a ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says somebody
was like banging on a door and somebody was saying who's being
מחלל שבת? mechalel Shabbos? because of the noise of banging on a
door. but anyway the general interpretation is much more like רש"י. Rashi.
okay that there's one thing about pursuing your pursuits and there's another
thing about just the things you're talking about. all right. דיבור אסור
הרהור מותר. dibur assur hirhur muttar. talking is forbidden, you're allowed to
think.
I'm allowed to think about the מסכת Masechta I want to make
a סיום Siyum on?
yeah yeah you are. yeah. there's only so much we can there's
only so much we can control and that is reasonable to expect
people to control themselves.
not talk about it. right. בשלמא כולהו לחיי. bishlama kulhu l'chai. somebody
says okay I get all of that. I get I get you
know what the application would be.
אלא שלא יהא הילוכך בשבת כהילוכך בחול ela shelo yehei hiluchecha b'Shabbos
k'hiluchecha b'chol that your going on שבת Shabbos shouldn't be like you
go on the weekday- מאי? mai? what does that mean? so גמרא
Gemara says כי הא דאמר רב הונא אמר רב ואמרי לה אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה אמר רב הונא אמר רב היי מהלך בשבת
ופגע באמת המים. ki ha d'amar Rav Huna amar Rav v'amrei lah
amar Rav Adda bar Ahava amar Rav Huna amar Rav hai mahalich
b'Shabbos u'paga b'amat hamayim. you're walking on שבת Shabbos and you come
to a stream of water. אם יכול להניח רגלו ראשונה קודם שתעקר
שנייה im yachol l'haniach raglo rishona kodem she'te'aker shniyah if you can
basically step over the stream so your second foot goes on the
other bank before your first first foot has to be lifted off
the ground so you can do it in one big step, מותר
muttar it's permissible. ואם לאו אסור v'im lav assur and if not
it would not be because you'd have to jump or take a
really stretch yourself and that would be
not a like you know more relaxed walking.
so גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רבא matkif lah Rava so רבא
Rava asks היכי עביד heichi avid so what do you want the
guy to do? ליקוף likof you want him to walk around the
whole stream? קמפיש בהילוכא kampeish b'hilucha so you make him expend extra
effort. ליעבר l'eivar that he should cross through the water? זימנין דמיתווסי
מאנין במיא zimnin d'mitvasi manin b'maya sometimes his garments will become soiled
with water- ואתי לידי סחיטה v'ati lidei s'chita and he'll come to
wring them out. So anyway, this is the best solution in this
case. אלא בהא, Ella beha, you're right. In that case, כיון דלא
אפשר שפיר דמי, keivan d'lo efshar shapir dami, since there's no alternative,
it's fine to take that big step. Okay, that
אלא, Ella, כי דבעי מיניה רב מרבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. ki deba'ei
minei Rav me-Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yosi. But here would be the example
like what רב Rav asked רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי: Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi
Yosi: מהו לפסוע פסיעה גסה בשבת? mahu lifso'a pesiah gassah b'Shabbos? Can
I take a large step on שבת? Shabbos? אמר ליה, Amar lei,
he said back to him, וכי בחול מי הותר? ve-chi be-chol mi
hutar? Who ever said it was permissible in the weekday? שאני אומר,
she-ani omer, because I say,
פסיעה גסה נוטלת אחד מחמש מאות ממאור עיניו של אדם. pesiah gassah
noteles echad mi-chamesh meos mi-me'or einav shel adam. That a large step
removes one-five hundredth of a person's eyesight. ומהדרה ליה בקידושא דבי שמשי,
u-mahadra lei b'kiddusha d'bei shimshi, but you can get it
back with the קידושא דבי שמשי kiddusha d'bei shimshi on Friday night.
So רש"י Rashi says if you drink the wine from the קידוש,
Kiddush, that somehow returns it. So there, you don't know what it's
really... what it's really
about. Anyway, so, okay, one minute, let me just, I just want
to check רש"י Rashi on that.
Okay, so let's read a little bit more and then I'll go
back to it. בעא מיניה רבי מרבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Ba'ei minei
Rabbi me-Rabbi Yishmael be-Rabbi Yosi. מהו לאכול אדמה בשבת? mahu leechol adamah
b'Shabbos? So similar type of an exchange. Can you eat dirt on
שבת? Shabbos? Sometimes they would do that as some type of a...
there actually is a sickness where people think that they, where people
eat dirt. You know this? Where the body craves dirt? There is
some type of a medical condition.
They're missing some, some
something
very core to them.
Oh is that true?
I heard about that. But they're missing something in their diet.
Interesting, interesting. Okay. So anyway, let's say you were doing it for
a remedy purpose. אמר ליה, Amar lei, וכי בחול מי הותר? ve-chi
be-chol mi hutar? Who said you could do it on the weekday?
שאני אומר, she-ani omer, because I say, אף בחול אסור מפני שהוא
מלקה, af be-chol assur mipnei she-hu malkeh, because it causes sort of,
it's injurious to your health. Health, and then the גמרא's Gemara going
to go on with the dirt issue. So about the issue about
the פסיעה דקה, pesiah daka, I just do want to say that
whether it's forbidden on the weekday or not, or whether you could
say, you know, still the point is, is that on שבת, Shabbos,
yeah, there is a point about walking in a more patient, less
rushed fashion, not taking a huge step, certainly not running. There's an
interesting thing though, which is that the טור Tur I believe says,
I think it's quoted about הגהות מיימוניות, Gos Mimoni,
anyway, that, he says הבחורים, habachurim, young men that enjoy running,
for them you are allowed to run on שבת. Shabbos. Even though
you normally say it's forbidden to run. It's actually funny the גמרא
Gemara didn't mention running, it mentioned the big step, but it's in
the same category. The reason you said wow, and I also say
wow and it's a surprise, is again, the same way כבוד kavod
and עונג oneg are not always the same thing. Yeah, it's very
nice you know, you want to dress relaxed for עונג, oneg, you're
not doing כבוד. kavod. So the idea that you enjoy running, it
might be an עונג oneg for you that you enjoy running, but
that doesn't mean that it's כבוד. kavod. It doesn't mean that to
be running is a respectful way of, you know, experiencing שבת, Shabbos,
even if it's an enjoyable way of experiencing שבת. Shabbos. So it
is interesting that they didn't bring around running. There's other גמרות Gemaras
also about running for a דבר מצוה devar mitzvah on שבת. Shabbos.
So that's
one if you're late for מנחה? Mincha?
Yes, so that's okay. But anyway, it is interesting that this גמרא
Gemara doesn't mention it, it mentions the large step. I was trying
to, I have to admit I didn't have a chance, I remembered
I once heard a nice פשט, pshat, like Michael asked, you know,
what does גמרא Gemara really mean? I know, גמרא Gemara might really
mean that it really thinks it takes away your eyesight. But, that
just might have been its belief. But, but there is, I've heard
some nice more metaphorical interpretations of this, but I have to tell
you, I was not, didn't have a chance to look it up.
I don't remember them off the top of my head.
But, you know, I'll thus say one of the things, here, if
you want a little bit of a פשט, pshat, it could be,
you know, that if you're taking these large steps, meaning like you're
too busy running through life, then you are not having, you're not
having a chance to truly see everything that there is to see
and experience it fully, fully experience what, what you know, what is
around you. How that's reversed by the קידוש Kiddush on Friday night?
Not clear, because you're slowing down for the קידוש Kiddush on Friday
night.
Yeah, you know you bring it in, and you know you're all
like nice.
I understand. Okay, so, right, so everybody is free to figure out
their appropriate דרשה derasha for this. All right, I'm moving on. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this,
so we're talking about eating dirt. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר רב אמי: Amar Rav Ami: כל האוכל מעפרא דבבל כאילו
אוכל מבשר אבותיו. kol ha-ochel me-afra d'Bavel k'ilu ochel mi-bsar avosav. Anybody
who eats from the dirt of בבל, Bavel, it's as if you're
eating from the flesh of your fathers. Because you know, everybody was
buried in בבל, Bavel, and according to the מהרש"א, Maharsha, it says
it's not like in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, where it was very
clear where they were buried. Here they were buried all over, you
know, the people that were brought from the time of נבוכדנצר. Nevuchadnetzar.
So you're probably eating some of the decomposed stuff of your fathers,
which is a very lovely image. ויש אומרים כאילו אוכל שקצים ורמשים.
Ve-yesh omrim k'ilu ochel shekatzim u-remasim. Some say it's like you actually
ate, you know, rodents and forbidden food. Why? דכתיב: de-chsiv: וימח את
כל היקום. vayimach es kol ha-yekum. Everything dissolved in the מבול, Mabul,
and we're going to see in a minute, they understand that a
lot of the waters of the מבול Mabul washed to בבל. Bavel.
So you're, you're eating all those dissolved טרייף treif things in addition
to human, dissolved human flesh. דאמר ריש לקיש: D'amar Reish Lakish: למה
נקרא שמה שנער? lama nikra shema Shinar? Why was בבל, Bavel, another
name in the תורה Torah for בבל Bavel is שנער? Shinar? שכל
מתי מבול ננערו לשם. she-kol mesei mabul ninaru l'sham. All of the
dead of the מבול Mabul sort of were shaken out to there.
Because בבל Bavel was, was very low sea level and therefore the
assumption is everything. came to בבל Bavel and it was also very
wet. אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan למה נקרא שמה מצולה? lama
nikra shema Metzula? Why was it called מצולה? Metzula? שכל מתי מבול
נצללו לשם shekol metai mabul nitzlelu lesham because all of the, I
know, sure. Because all of the dead of the מבול mabul somehow
floated there. ויש אומרים כאילו אוכלין שקצים ורמשים, ve'yesh omrim ke'ilu ochlin
shkatzim u'remasim, so now going back to that line, והא בריי אסמחויי
אסמכו. ve'ha barei ismachuyei asmachu. What do you mean like you're eating
them? They definitely have dissolved, they're no longer considered to be שקצים
ורמשים. shkatzim u'remasim. So אמרי amri כיוון דמאלקי גזרו ביה רבנן. keivan
d'malki gazru beih rabanan. You're right, it's really not like you ate
שקצים ורמשים. shkatzim u'remasim. But because eating dirt is injurious to your
health, they said that if you did it, it's like you ate
שקצים ורמשים. shkatzim u'remasim. It's interesting the phrase they use גזרו ביה
רבנן. gazru beih rabanan. We would have said like that's why they
used that rhetoric because they want to, you know, get you to
avoid eating dirt. Here it's making it almost like rabbinically it's like
you ate these טרייף treif animals. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is
but these things it's really not like you did that, it's a
way of getting people not to eat dirt. It is interesting if
they needed rhetoric to stop people from eating dirt then clearly they
were doing it, which might really show, like Rivka said, you know,
that they you're dealing with a lot of poverty possibly. Okay, but
it is fascinating to imagine why are people eating dirt? Maybe again
there was some folk remedy. ההוא גברא דאכל גרגשתא ואכל תכלי hahu
gavra d'achal gargashta v'achal tichli וקדחו
תכליא בלביה ומית. v'kadchu tichlaya b'libeih u'meis. Okay, so there was a
person that ate, I don't know, what's English translation you have for
this?
What's... Gray clay? Clay, yeah.
And he ate, and he ate cress. Right. And it sprouted up
in his heart.
Thank you. Okay, right. So he basically he ate clay and he
ate cress and then it's like you know it was like a
fever.
The
cress caused a fever in his heart and he died. So don't
eat dirt.
Well, did this just, I actually have to say this, just a
little bit ago this guy he swallowed some sort of thing and
it was like a seed, it literally grew inside of him.
Right, so that's what רש״י Rashi says. רש״י Rashi says קדחו תכלי
נקלטו התכלים באדמה וגידלו בני אב. kadchu tichli nikletu ha'tichlim b'adama v'gidlu
bnei av. Okay, that actually the plant took root in the dirt
and ruined his body. You're saying something like that really happened?
Not dirt but he actually swallowed a seed and they went to
some sort of exam, he had like this little plant growing in
his body.
How does the stomach enzymes, the acid in the stomach...
They actually had a picture of it.
Oh my god. Okay well that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is
saying.
חייא בר זוריא. Hiyya bar Zorya.
Okay, moving on. And that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. He
ate dirt and a plant planted in his body and it grew
out of the dirt. Okay, now moving on. Back to שבת Shabbos
clothes. ורחצת וסכת ושמת שמלותיך. v'rachatzat v'sacht v'shamt simlotaich. You should bathe
and anoint yourself and put on your garments. This is what נעמי
Naomi says to רות. Rus. אמר רבי אלעזר אלו בגדים של שבת.
amar Rabbi Elazar elu begadim shel Shabbos. So your garments, these are
the special garments, your שבת Shabbos garments. Of course you have to
get dressed. What do you mean your garments? Everybody gets dressed. No,
it means your special garments, your שבת Shabbos garments.
Fine, תן לחכם ויחכם עוד. ten l'chacham v'yichkam od. Now we're going
to have another דרשה drasha going now to about this רות Rus
story. Now we're going to be on a רות Rus discussion. Okay,
so give to the wise person, they'll be, and they'll add, you
know, they'll take it one step further. אמר רבי אלעזר זו רות
המואביה ושמואל הרמתי. amar Rabbi Elazar zo Rus ha'Moaviya u'Shmuel ha'Ramati. This
is proved by רות Rus and by שמואל. Shmuel. רות דאילו נעמי
קאמרה לה, Rus d'ilu Naomi ka'amra lah, נעמי Naomi said to her
ורחצת וסכת ושמת שמלותיך עליך וירדת הגורן. v'rachatzat v'sacht v'shamt simlotaich alaich
v'yaradt ha'goren. Wash and bathe and get dressed and go down to
the threshing house. ואילו בדידה כתיב, v'ilu b'dida ksiv, when she did
it, she improved on her mother-in-law's plan. ותרד הגורן. v'tered ha'goren. It
says first she went down, והדר ותעש ככל אשר צותה חמותה. v'hadar
vata'as k'chol asher tzivata chamota. And then she did all that. Why
did she do it the reverse? So רש״י Rashi says basically not
to announce to everybody like here, what is she doing so dressed
up so beautifully and going down into the threshing house? So this
was much more private she did it once she was already there,
she found a private place to do it. שמואל, Shmuel, ועל שמואל
v'al Shmuel remember שמואל Shmuel the first the beginning of the story
of שמואל, Shmuel, I mean after he's born, is that he's in
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and here or the משכן Mishkan and
he hears a voice calling out to him, you know, and he
says הנני הנני, hineni hineni, he doesn't know what it is and
he goes to עלי Eli and עלי Eli says it's God calling.
He first he thought it was maybe עלי Eli calling to him.
So anyway דאילו עלי קאמר ליה, d'ilu Eli ka'amar leih, עלי Eli
says here's what you do. שכב, shchav, go back to sleep, והיה
אם יקרא אליך v'haya im yikra eilecha if this voice calls out
to you,
ואמרת דבר ה׳ כי שומע עבדך. v'amarta daber Hashem ki shomeia avdecha.
I hear, acknowledge that you're hearing, דבר ה׳. daber Hashem.
Yeah, go speak God, speak to me, tell me what you want.
Oh, I'm sorry, thank you, right, okay. דבר ה׳ כי שומע עבדך.
daber Hashem ki shomeia avdecha. So speak God because I am listening.
ואילו בדידה כתיב v'ilu b'dida ksiv when he did it, he says
ויבוא ה׳
ויתייצב
ויקרא כפעם בפעם v'yavo Hashem v'yityatzeiv v'yikra k'fa'am b'fa'am and God came
and called out to him like He did in the past. שמואל
שמואל ויאמר שמואל דבר
כי שומע עבדך. Shmuel Shmuel v'yomar Shmuel daber ki shomeia avdecha. Speak
because I am listening. ולא אמר דבר ה׳ v'lo amar daber Hashem
because he didn't want to say God's name, maybe he would say
it without, you know, without a need, or רש״י Rashi says maybe
he wasn't, maybe it was a way of of doing what עלי
Eli said without even though he wasn't a hundred percent confident it
really was God's voice, so he left out the ה׳. Hashem.
ותלך ותבוא v'telech v'tavo now we're back to רות, Rus, ותלך ותבוא
ותלקט בשדה, v'telech v'tavo v'tilakeit ba'sadei, she came and she went and
she gathered in the field. אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar what
does it mean she came and she went... So say she went
and she gathered in the field. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rebbe Elazar,
what does it mean she came and she went? So say she
went and she gathered in the field. שהלכה ובאתה הלכה ובאתה, Shehalcha
uvata halcha uvata, she came and she went, she came and she
went, she was looking all around עד שמצאה בני אדם המהוגנים לילך
עמהם, Ad shematza benei adam hamhuganim layelech imahem, until she found a
proper group of people to go with. She didn't just go with
anybody, she needed to go with right people, you know, modest people
as we'll see in a minute, the right type of people. ויאמר
בועז לנערו, Vayomer Boaz l'na'aro, so Boaz said, again, we're off of
Shabbos and Shabbos clothes, which is how we got onto this, we're
onto Ruth. Boaz said to his young man הנצב על הקוצרים hanitzav
al hakotzrim that stood over the harvesters, למי הנערה הזאת, Lemi hana'ara
hazot, to whom is that young woman? So the Gemara says, וכי
דרכו של בועז לשאול בנערה, Vchi darko shel Boaz lishol b'na'ara, what,
Boaz was asking after women? Well, according to the story, I guess,
but okay. So, but anyway, the way Rashi says it's like only
if he was in the practice of checking out the women would
he have noticed her. So, what's going on?
He was single, he was looking for...
Alright, okay, and it's true, you're allowed to look for... Anyway, אמר
רבי אלעזר, Amar Rebbe Elazar, דבר חכמה ראה בה. dvar chochma ra'a
ba. No, he—she caught his attention not because of her looks or
that he was looking at the women, but the way she was
acting. What does it mean? שני שבלים לקטה, Shenei shibolim likta, if
she had two
stalks she—that was—she gathered it. שלשה שבלים אינה לקטה, Shlosha shibolim eina
likta, she didn't do three, for three isn't. Halachically only two that
are dropped are, not three. So oh my God, she really knows
her stuff, and maybe she's also careful about the halacha not to
take things that aren't hers. ובמתניתא תנא, Uvmatnita tana, in a baraita
we taught, דבר צניעות ראה בה, dvar tzniyut ra'a ba, he saw
that she was very modest. עומדת מעומד, Omedet me'umad, when she gathered
the leftover standing stalks, she was standing. נופלות מיושב, Noflot meyoshav, the
stalks that had fallen down that she was gathering, she wouldn't bend
over, she would rather crouch down in order to pick them up
in a more modest way. Okay, ותדבקי עם נערותי, Vatidbaki im na'arotai,
and then he says to her you should cleave to my young
lasses. וכי דרכו של בועז לדבק, אימא לדבר עם הנשים, Vchi darko
shel Boaz ledabek, eima ledaber im hanashim, he wasn't the one that
was cleaving, he told her to cleave. But anyway, what does it
mean "my lasses" and what does he—why is he talking to her?
Maybe he had somebody else talk to her. So אמר רבי אלעזר,
Amar Rebbe Elazar, כיוון דחזא, keivan d'chaza,
once he saw ותשק ערפה לחמותה ורות דבקה בה. vatishak Orpa lachamota
v'Rut davka ba. So again, it's a play on the word,
right, to cleave and to cleave. אמר, Amar, שרי לאדבוקי בה. shari
l'idbuki ba. Oh, this is somebody that you should be cleaving to.
Again, it's funny, she's not the one cleaving to her, but the
point is the use of the word of cleave with a man
speaking to a woman seems inappropriate. But the Gemara's saying because it's
really reflecting back the use of the word earlier. ויאמר לה בועז
לעת האוכל, Vayomer la Boaz l'et ha'ochel, Boaz said to her at
the time of eating, גשי הלום, goshi halom, draw near.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rebbe Elazar, רמז רמז לה, remez ramaz la,
he hinted to her, עתידה מלכות בית דוד לצאת ממך, atida malchut
beit David latzet mimech, eventually the kingdom of David will come from
you. And now Rashi said he didn't intend this. This was like
מן השמים, min hashamayim, you know, he used the words that the
words indicated this. He wasn't intending it. Eventually the kingship of David
will come from you, דכתיב ביה הלום, dchtiv bei halom, that uses
this word, שנאמר, shenemar, as it says, ויבא המלך דוד וישב לפני
ה' ויאמר מי אנכי ה' אלוקים ומי ביתי כי הביאתני עד הלום.
Vayavo hamelech David vayeishev lifnei Hashem vayomer mi anochi Hashem Elokim umi
veiti ki hevi'atani ad halom. Who am I that you have brought
me until? So it's the same echo. וטבלת פתך בחומץ, V'tavalt pitech
bachometz, you should dip your bread in vinegar. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar
Rebbe Elazar, מכאן שהחומץ יפה לשרב, mikan shehachometz yafeh l'sharav, you see
that vinegar is good for heatstroke, or as you know, it's very
hot. ורבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר, V'Rebbe Shmuel bar Nachmani amar, רמז
רמז לה, remez ramaz la, no, again this was a hint, again
not necessarily he was intending it, but it was a hint. עתיד
בן לצאת ממך שמעשיו קשים כחומץ, Atid ben latzet mimech shema'asav kashim
k'chometz, you will have one son that will be as bad as
vinegar. ומנו מנשה. Umanu Menashe. Okay. ותשב מצד הקוצרים, Vateshev mitzad hakotzrim,
she sat by the side of the harvesters. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar
Rebbe Elazar, מצד הקוצרים, mitzad hakotzrim, by their side, ולא בתוך הקוצרים,
v'lo betoch hakotzrim, not in their midst. The way Rashi explains it
is that Boaz was at one end and then you had all
the harvesters and Ruth was at the other end. They were very
separate from one another. רמז רמז לה, Remez ramaz la, he hinted
to her שעתידה מלכות בית דוד שתהא מתחלקת, she'atida malchut beit David
shetehei metchaleket, eventually the kingdom of David would split.
How do you get that from?
Because they're split, Boaz and Ruth were at opposite ends. ויצבט לה
קלי, Vayitzbat la kali, he—he like handed her a little bit, ותאכל,
vatocal, and she ate.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rebbe Elazar, ותאכל בימי דוד, vatocal bimei David,
meaning that it was wealthy—there was a lot of wealth in the
time of David, ותשבע vatisba is the next word in the pasuk,
really satisfied בימי שלמה, bimei Shlomo, ותותר vatotar and there was leftover,
the full degree of like wealth, בימי חזקיה. bimei Chizkiyahu. I thought
Shlomo was the biggest... I know, but ואיכא דאמרי, V'ika d'amri, some
say, ותאכל בימי דוד ובימי שלמה, vatocal bimei David uvimei Shlomo, stage
one was and, ותשבע vatisba to be satisfied,
בימי חזקיה, bimei Chizkiyahu, ותותר vatotar leftover, the greatest wealth, בימי רבי,
bimei Rebbe, which is amazing. Think about that, Rebbe, the wealth of
Rebbe was greater than the wealth of Shlomo and Chizkiyahu. Maybe it
means personal wealth, maybe it doesn't mean the country's wealth, but the
personal wealth, let's say. Or maybe it's his Torah. What? No, I
don't think so. דאמר מר, D'amar mar, because we've said,
אהורייא דרבי, ahoreiya d'Rebbe, the—I think it says one of the people
in charge of his—of his—of his horses or his camels or whatever,
anyway, הוה
עתיר hava atir ממשבור מלכא mi-Shvur Malka was richer than Shvur Malka
which was the—which was the
king.
במתניתא תנא Bi-matneisa tana and the ברייתא Baraisa we taught, ותאכל בעולם
הזה Vetochal ba-olam ha-zeh ותשבע לימות המשיח vetisba l'yemos Hamashiach ותותר לעתיד
לבוא. vesosar l'asid lavo. Back to שבת Shabbos back tomorrow.
Okay.